[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
this episode of se radio is exclusively
sponsored by lenoir the node makes cloud
computing simple affordable and
accessible whether you're working on a
personal project or looking for someone
to manage your company's infrastructure
lenode has the pricing support security
and scale you need with lenod you get
consistent and predictable pricing
across 11 global markets 24x7 by 365
human support rich documentation and
policies and controls to strengthen your
overall security posture allowing you to
grow at your own pace users consistently
rank lenode as one of the leading public
cloud providers on both g2 and trust
radius want to learn more about
infrastructure as code and terraform
visit lenode.com that's l-i-n-o-d-e
s-e-radio and download their e-book
understanding terraform and other
resources for free today
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff doolittle
i'm excited to invite luke hoban as our
guest on the show today for a
conversation about infrastructure as
code
luke hobin is the cto at palumi where he
is reinventing how developers program
the cloud prior to pollumi luke held
product and engineering roles at aws and
microsoft
at microsoft luke co-founded typescript
developed ghost support for visual
studio code and was part of the design
teams for ecmascript and c-sharp luke is
passionate about building tools and
platforms to enable and empower
developers and is a deep believer in the
transformative potential of the cloud
luke welcome to software engineering
radio thanks great to be here we've had
some shows in the past and we'll
reference them in the show notes that
have talked about infrastructure as code
and just for listeners who maybe aren't
familiar with the concept first we might
use the phrase or the three-letter
acronym iac throughout the show to refer
to infrastructure as code but let's
start with from your perspective a brief
overview of
what is iac
for listeners who are new to the concept
and also why does it matter
infrastructure's code is really the idea
that we want to take the cloud
infrastructure that we're managing and
we want to encode it as code not just as
something where we point and click in a
console and create some stuff in a sort
of ad hoc fashion
where we write down in text and in
programming languages in software and
encode the way that we want our cloud
infrastructure to run and i really think
about this is sort of bringing the
notions of software engineering into the
space of cloud infrastructure and we've
sort of seen how software engineering
principles practices and tools have
enabled us in lots of other areas to
scale up the complexity of what we can
build and manage and sort of get value
out of and we really want to do that
same thing with the cloud as the as we
want to build more and more complex
things that have more and more value and
get more and more benefit from what the
cloud providers are offering to us one
of the core things we need to do is
bring some of those software engineering
tools to bear on that so what are some
of those specific software engineering
principles or practices that you would
highlight as beneficial in this kind of
an approach yes i think some of the
traditional ones when folks think about
just infrastructure's code as it's
traditionally been even from the kind of
chef and puppet and ansible era to the
sort of terraform and pollution cloud
formation and that sort of thing
i think folks often think about the
first piece being hey i can take my
description of what i want my
infrastructure to be and i can write
that down in text i can put that in a
file i can put that file in source
control so you start to get some of
these basic things where i can describe
my desired state describe what i want
instead of me having to just describe a
set of steps where to click in a console
or something like that i can write it
down in a format that i conversion and i
can version control that's where
infrastructure's code i think really
started and tons of value you get just
from sort of that aspect right that's
seeing a huge you know rise in and the
complexity of what folks will be able to
manage but i think really when i think
about it you know i kind of joined the
infrastructure's code movement i'd say
kind of after that phase had already
been well established and and now we're
sort of looking more at what are the
other places where we can bring software
engineering benefits in and there i
think it's a whole bunch of additional
things like hey what about versioning
and packaging what about testing what
about you know the ability to build
reusable components this is something
that software is really great at right
we can instead of reinventing the wheel
every time we can kind of go and solve a
problem give it a name give that
function a name give that class a name
put that in a package we use that from
from nuget or npm or something how do we
componentize how do we create
abstractions then how do we get ide
benefits so that we can sort of
productively work with the platform how
do we get all these other things that
software engineering gives us how do we
bring all that into you know scaling up
what we can do with cloud infrastructure
and so for me that's what iac really is
all about
yeah so you covered a bunch of things
there many of which we'll get to in the
show and when you started out i kind of
sense a distinction there between
basically a declarative approach versus
an imperative approach you know the
imperative is you're literally saying
provision this resource if we're talking
about infrastructure versus declaring is
there is a resource or there will be
such a resource and it seems like that's
that's one of the distinctions that
you're drawing at least where things
have moved in the iac movement and then
that's interesting to you related it to
making it work with existing developer
tools there at the end as sort of a way
to leverage maybe the knowledge that
software teams already have as they're
adopting these kinds of approaches yeah
i think both of those are great points
and on the first one they're about kind
of declarative versus imperative one of
the interesting things with iac
generally is i often think of it as
really that the core thing that i see is
fundamentally is a desired state thing
and i don't think about that purely as
being about declarative or imperative
it's more that the thing i'm describing
is the desired state of the environment
and that's particularly important
because unlike a normal you know piece
of software that i might write where i
sort of run it and it ends at some point
and maybe the process dies or something
and i start it up again with
infrastructure's code and cloud
infrastructure it's it's there forever
if i say i want to have an s3 bucket
well that has three buckets gonna be
there forever effectively
yeah my infrastructure programs are
things that describe the desire today
when i make changes to those it's
actually sort of changing the
program that's running the whole time
right and so it's sort of this
interestingly different model for kind
of how i think about it and the
fundamental part of that i think is that
what you're doing is you're describing
what's the desired state i want now and
when i make changes to that desired
state how do i get from where i am to
that desired state and then i think kind
of in front of that the feel of the
experience of authoring infrastructure's
code i think there's some tools that
really lean on a very
very declarative model they sort of
invent a dsl or they use json or yaml or
something like that to have a very
declarative feeling interface to that
desired state model but i think tools
like what we work on at palumi things
like cdk that abs is working on they
actually provide an imperative
experience for users where they can sort
of use a lot more of this richness
software engineering capabilities and
software-based capabilities but they're
still defining the desired state they're
just using higher level primitives to
kind of do that in more expressive
languages and so i think you know for me
i think that whole spectrum of different
ways that users might interact with
infrastructure code is really
interesting but at the end of the day i
think the defining characteristic there
is hey but it's a desired state model
i'm describing what state i want my
infrastructure to be in and the
underlying iac tool is going to is going
to move my cloud infrastructure into
that state that's a great clarification
and i'm glad you mentioned the concept
of desired state because i've heard that
as well kind of in this realm that
that's really what we want and that'd be
great if we could just do that into the
world as well right into the universe
here's my desired state and it just
happens but you know i guess we're still
working on that we've seen some of how
it matters right i mean you mentioned
other things like reuse componentization
these kinds of things which is all great
stuff that we all really want to be able
to benefit from not having to reinvent
the wheel all the time so listeners are
going to be all over the place some are
going to be doing existing applications
and some are going to be building new
applications but give us a sense of if
somebody's interested in exploring the
space where would they get started the
great thing about iec is there's you
know a ton of different on-ramps right
everything from hey let's imagine that
you've got a whole bunch of existing
infrastructure that you have just kind
of point and click you've gone in the
console you know you had to get a
project up and running as quickly as
possible so you clicked a few times you
created your bucket you created your
your web app whatever it was and now
you're kind of realizing oh well i don't
exactly know what i'm managing here i
don't exactly know how to reliably
recreate this environment because i want
a test environment that matches this
like how am i going to go and create
that and so it's probably around that
point that you're realizing oh i this is
where i kind of need infrastructure's
code or i need some some way to describe
what i've got to repeatably recreate it
to understand when i when and how to
make changes to it that sort of thing
now there's a few things one there's a
lot of ways to go and export what you've
got inside these cloud environments
tools like polumi a lot of the other ise
tools have ways to sort of import
existing infrastructure into the tool
when he has a plumbing import command
similar things in a lot of other isc
tools where you can kind of go and take
existing things you've built and sort of
bring them into that iac environment and
start managing them with your iac even
if they didn't start off in life managed
by an isc tool there's also a lot of
folks who they take the approach more of
hey i've got my existing stuff which i'm
going to leave alone i know what state
that's in
but i've got this new stuff i'm going to
build or i'm extending my application to
have some new components maybe i'm
adding in a new service or i'm adding a
new capability new caching layer or
something like that that new project i'm
going to kind of use iac from the
beginning but i'm going to reference
some of that existing infrastructure
typically a lot of these iac tools offer
a lot of different ways to discover
existing infrastructure bind into that
and kind of use it from the new piece
that you're you're building using these
tools the key thing is really that just
learning how to use the iac tools and i
think you know for palumi we've got you
know flumi.com getting started you know
you can go there you can go through a
really quick you know five minutes
you'll kind of have a simple application
stood up in your cloud environment and
then you can go through that process of
hey how do i use this tool to map to my
problems not just these sort of generic
problems if you've got any amount of
sort of software engineering kind of
background i think these tools tend to
be you know pretty easy to pick up
really as with everything in the cloud a
lot of the complexity comes down to just
all the value all the concepts that
you've got in that cloud environment all
the tools you've got available to you to
pick up off the ground and leverage and
that's where you can use the ise tools
to help you explore and discover and
sort of tame them yeah and that's great
to hear that listeners can get started
haven't we all you use whatever portals
available to you from the vendor and
then after a while you say this isn't
very sustainable you know i've seen
teams where
okay i have to remember pushing the
buttons in the same order in production
as we go live that i pushed them in
devon and test and the odds of you
getting it right are actually quite low
and the more complex the system is the
likelihood plummets so the ability to
adopt these things with existing systems
seems really helpful
now there's also more movement towards
command line interface which i'm a big
fan of i like command line and being
able to drop down to the command line
but maybe distinguish a little bit as
well there between i've got the pretty
gui with azure or google cloud or aws
and then i've got the command line which
is pretty powerful but next thing you
know i'm writing bash scripts to
automate my you know my command line so
talk a little bit there about two maybe
where's the line i guess like what i'm
saying is i feel like the line is clear
for me between the gui and some kind of
automation but the clies can sort the
command line interfaces they can kind of
give you the sense of well i am doing
infrastructure as code but maybe
distinguish those for a little bit when
you'd say no it's really time to
graduate from just using the cli and
start using an isc tool that's a great
point there are really several different
steps here i think there's there is this
sort of ui driven thing where you're
just kind of pointing and clicking
around then there is the bash scripts or
the powershell scripts or whatever
whatever it is like that that is just
you know shelling out to aws cli
commands or something like that right
one of the troubles that that kind of
scripting based approach runs into is
just that it is very fundamentally
imperative in the sense that i'm bashing
on the cloud apis right
i see what you did there yes i'm gonna
do this i'm gonna do this i'm gonna do
this and the problem is well what
happens if my environment ends up in a
slightly different state or if i make a
change to how those scripts work and i
need to handle the fact that i had an
already provisioned environment i don't
get to just provision my environment
from scratch every time it's that notion
of hey can i move from one state to
another reliably
is something that the tools that are
built around sort of the scripting kind
of solutions tend to not handle well and
that leads to fragility it leads to you
know especially fragility in the cases
where hey there's some operational issue
and i've got to get some change out but
oh my script doesn't quite handle that
approach yet so now i'm now i'm rushing
to fix my scripts in the middle of an
operational it's always the worst time
exactly yeah that was early cloud and
sort of pre-cloud vm based era there was
a lot of that where folks you know the
majority of what folks did in
infrastructure management was these kind
of scripting approaches and that's still
very very common but we find for almost
everyone who's managing anything with a
meaningful amount of complexity to it
that's practically anyone trying to
really use the cloud today
they find that those kind of tools don't
scale super well and that they do need
to have something there's a bit more
kind of desire to stay focused that is
able to take an existing piece of
infrastructure move it into the state
they want that's a key distinction i
think we see there's always going to be
little bits of this scripting you know
just any i mean those operational tasks
all sorts of things that you're going to
need to sort of be imperative actions
that you take and you're always going to
have a little bit of that around the
edges but we find that folks the more
they can pull into sort of iac tools the
more confident they feel about what
they're managing in the cloud so really
at the end of the day that's going to
come down to
managing the complexity which as you
point out as soon as you go cloud you're
introducing orders of magnitude of
additional complexity unless you just
you know run a single vm in which case
it's really barely the cloud and then
you have to consider maybe poking away
at the gui is good for exploring what's
available but when it comes down to
managing
routers and vpns and compute and storage
and all and buses and all this stuff
then it starts to get pretty daunting
pretty quickly and i imagine one of the
things is are trying to do too is create
some amount of consistency if if every
team has their own custom yaml or toml
file or json or whatever and their own
custom scripts that also adds complexity
that's hard to maintain and a burden of
training and you know the person who
wrote it leaves and nobody knows what it
does so i imagine that's also something
that isctools are trying to help with as
well absolutely it's one of the
interesting things i remember seeing
kind of when i came into this
specifically i i came from a background
working on developer tools mostly for
application developers and kind of
program languages and ids and developer
tools and that sort of thing and coming
into the cloud infrastructure space you
know is kind of amazed how much of what
gets done is copy-pasting stuff around
right you if you went to an application
development team and they said oh yeah
we solved that problem by copy-pasting a
couple hundred lines of code from this
code base over this code base
like everyone would laugh you out of the
room right you're not allowed to do that
if you're an application developer right
you gotta you know do it but yes it
should do it yeah that's not the
standard the standard is oh i'm gonna
make a reusable library i'm gonna find
something on mpm that accomplishes this
task i'm gonna use that instead of
reinventing that wheel or copy pasting
it out of that code base we have lots of
great tools available to us for how to
do this and so that notion of reuse of
abstraction is sort of so deep in what
we think about for application
development and still that's not in the
cloud infrastructure space we do see a
lot of copy pasting here's this 300
lines of code i wrote in a yaml file
over here i'm just going to copy paste
that and put it over here as well that's
good the first time maybe but the 100th
time now you've made a change over here
all these things are diverging instead
of having 100 lines of code you imagine
you've got 10 000 lines of code you're
managing and it just creates a ton of
risk and complexity and management
overhead and so that's where we sort of
see hey like these are things we know
how to solve we know how to bring kind
of software engineering tools in
how to bring program languages ids you
know packaging those kind of things in
to to help with these problems and to
give folks the ability to kind of manage
those problems as they scale up that's
great so you referenced before kind of
almost like there's two phases maybe
it's not two but some kind of like
there's a sort of early phase early
stage chef puppet ansible which are
still around and then there's what you
kind of refer to as this second maybe
phase paloomy terraform so maybe tell us
a little bit about what distinguishes
sort of those two time frames in your
mind and then also what kind of
distinguishes say a palumi from a
terraform and those other players in
this space as well great question um and
maybe i'll split it actually into sort
of my view on kind of three phases of
this in a sense i think you know the
first one is sort of pre-cloud or early
cloud where really most folks were
managing think of it as more vm based
architectures right where they were
managing a couple of vms typically they
knew you know it was very much the pets
not the cattle what those vms were the
work of the team managing that
application was to run the right
software inside that vm and they were
just responsible for all that they
wanted to make sure they did that
reliably and repeatably so they were
using iac they're using things like chef
and puppet to sort of orchestrate how
they deployed things inside that vm but
it was all about code running inside a
virtual machine and fairly simple
topologies outside of the virtual
machine maybe there's a database and a
single vm or a couple of vms but
generally a pretty simple infrastructure
outside of that that's mainly
managed imperatively through you know
vmware or something like that sure that
was sort of the first phase where iac
started to become a thing i think then
there was sort of the early cloud phase
where a lot of those patterns moved into
the cloud and there was more
api driven capabilities inside the cloud
providers and so the networking and
compute and everything can be
provisioned via api and so now you sort
of had terraform and cloud formation and
arm and things like that come about as
ways to
put desired state in front of all these
new pieces of the system that were
programmable
but still the level of complexity of
what folks were building there was
typically not that high right it was
typically maybe i've got tens of things
i'm managing i've got my vm i've got my
auto scaling group and some networking
pieces but i've got a fairly discreet
set of things they don't change that
often i can be pretty intentional and
sort of slow in a sense with how i
manage these i'd say with a phase we're
kind of going into now that a lot of
organizations who are really leaning
into the cloud are going into it i think
really everyone is going to be heading
towards is what i sort of think of as
modern cloud and that's sort of the the
containers kubernetes serverless these
modern technologies have been built to
not just be in the cloud but sort of be
native to the cloud and it's not just
lift and shift my vm architecture into
the cloud and get some api driven
capabilities it's hey i take a totally
different approach to the architecture
of how i build and deliver my software
to take advantage of what the cloud
provides and the interesting thing with
those architectures is
they tend to lean a lot more heavily on
me composing a bunch of managed services
either managed compute services like
with serverless or managed data services
or managed sort of fully baked services
whether it's like ml services or
something like that
and what happens there is that a lot of
the complexity ends up moving from i no
longer have to manage it i don't like no
longer have to run that vm myself and
put the software in that thing myself
and manage that and so some of that
complexity that i had to manage before
goes away and that's an operational
burden off of me and that lets me move a
lot faster and market quicker
where the burden moves though is
actually into the edges between all
those services right the way that i
connect s3 to ec2 to lambda to you know
redshift a lot of the complexity is now
and how do i compose all these pieces of
value i've got in the cloud and it's
that complexity that is what iac is all
about it's about how do i connect all
these things right about what cloud ise
is about the what things like
preliminary and so for me that's the
really interesting place where we're
kind of going to is
we're actually benefiting a ton from all
these managed services from all these
modern cloud technologies and it's net
reducing the complexity but we build a
lot by taking all this operational
burden off us but the one place where
it's sort of pushing some of that
additional complexity is into the
configuration of how all these things
are connected together
and so that's causing the need for more
and more sort of infrastructure more
more scale in the infrastructure's code
management that's where we see folks
looking for tools like polonius hey i'm
just realizing that to build this modern
cloud solution
i need to manage hundreds thousands tens
of thousands of cloud resources i need
those to be versioning and changing
every day or every few hours this is a
software problem this is not a just an
infrastructure this is a software
problem and we have to figure out
software tools to solve it that's a good
perspective and you know you mentioned
complexity it reminds me of larry
tesler's law of conservation of
complexity which we'll reference in the
show notes which is basically says you
never get rid of complexity you just
move it around and hide it right and the
reason say your car is easy to use is
because all the complexity is behind the
dashboard and under the hood and in a
similar fashion right we're not getting
rid of it but we see it shifting and
moving into places that now need to be
addressed in different ways i think the
great thing also is this complexity
isn't isn't coming out of nowhere in a
sense it's coming because folks are
getting more and more value out of the
cloud yeah building blocks are so
valuable right they're letting them
deliver more quickly deliver more
reliably deliver more securely so folks
want to go and take advantage of all
this stuff but the one cost of that as
they extract that value and as they try
to attract more and more value is just
that there is more complexity there is
more stuff that they've got to connect
up together absolutely maybe talk a
little bit now about what distinguishes
those we talked kind of about the
history and sort of where things have
been and where they're going so what
distinguishes maybe the different
vendors in this space of how they
approach iec what do they emphasize
different tooling things of that nature
the one probably most consistent thing
for anything that sort of thinks of
itself as an iac tool is this notion of
kind of having a desired state model and
describing the state of the world and so
then within that i think there's some of
the traditional tools that we're really
focused on largely in guest provisioning
and os provisioning and that kind of
thing then there's sort of another set
that's really focused on cloud
management so managing cloud apis and
the configuration of different cloud
services and so i think that's one place
where there's a differentiation you've
got your you know chef and puppets on
one side and you've got your terraforms
and cloud formations and arms on the
other side within that second camp of
kind of managing the cloud i didn't
think there's one big category that's
sort of about is the interface to that
you know we talked about this earlier is
the interface of that declarative model
or kind of a software-based model and
you know there's a set of tools like you
know cloud formation and arm obviously
using json and yaml as kind of a way to
describe that
fairly limited domain specific languages
really meant to be about more treating
the infrastructure as data than treating
the software in a sense and that that's
good at small scales um but that may be
you know is more difficult at very large
scales and then you've got tools like
terraform which have their own domain
specific language it's not quite json
yam it's a bit more expressive than that
but it's also not quite as expressive as
traditional kind of application
development languages and then tools
like pollumi that i work on and the aws
cdk these are tools that let you use
existing programming languages that you
may already be familiar with typescript
pythongo.net
and use those environments to manage the
desired state of your infrastructure and
so for a lot of
application developers both folks who
already have or understand that their
scale is such that they need these tools
to manage complexity or they have that
background of working in one of those
software ecosystems and they want to
continue to leverage the test tools and
the packaging tools and the
componentization tools and ide tooling
that they're used to those tools can be
great for them so those are sort of some
of the big categories that i think kind
of differentiate some of the existing
tools yeah back to what you mentioned
before about adopting good software
engineering principles here with that
approach you're kind of mentioning at
the end seems like it fits better in a
productive developer flow where
well we send in pull requests and we do
code reviews and we test these things
and we do security audits on them it
seems like that approach can maybe kind
of dovetail is that i mean that's kind
of point right
i think a lot of teams already have good
software engineering practices around
their you know their.net code bases and
their typescript code bases and what
have you the things you were just
talking about the pull request workflows
and that sort of thing but also the
testing the continuous integration they
have a package manager somewhere maybe
it's artifactory or something like that
they have all these things set up to
kind of manage their software for their
application side with this class of
tools that kind of pollutes in you can
kind of go and reuse all those and teams
are
more likely to go and sort of reuse
those and say hey i think i should be
testing my infrastructure because i know
how to test using the tools i've got
available to me in c sharp how can i
apply that now to my infrastructure
because i'm doing that in c-sharp as
well yeah well from there let's segue
then into okay i've decided to adopt i
see whether it's a brand new system or
an existing system that i'm going to
kind of do side by side or convert
whatever it might be
so now if i'm adopting this approach of
code that represents the desired state
of my infrastructure
what are the ways people manage these
definitions it's one thing to say well
you write code okay you write code
but are there distinctions maybe between
standard engineering practices are there
also similarities how do people start to
think through okay i'm going to do this
how do i organize and maintain
the set of descriptions of desired state
it starts in the same way that a lot of
application development might start that
hey you know i might start with a very
simple program where i've got kind of
one code base it's got all the logic for
what i want to build out but over time i
might realize that there's some pieces
of this that are actually reusable
components and that's actually easier
for me to understand what i'm doing here
if i take this subset of my application
code factor it out give it a name give
it a nice interface and now it's easier
for folks to both understand and test
and validate that piece but also to more
easily understand what the kind of full
application is doing because it's now
framed in terms of higher level building
blocks
and so i think the same sort of thing
really happens with infrastructure's
code where teams will generally start by
just kind of building out their
infrastructure writing it down as code
and kind of just a flat format as it
grows as they evolve as they understand
where the sort of versioning boundaries
are where the sort of abstractions are
in what they're building when they stand
up their third kind of micro service or
something they realize oh well a micro
service is actually this set of five
things right so maybe i should give that
that notion a name and now i can sort of
make improvements across all of those
pieces if i if i do it in one place
and so we see that sort of a lot of that
same evolutionary path in terms of how
do i manage that code base tends to
happen and folks who kind of come into
these problems with a bit of an
engineering mindset tend to be able to
apply those tools and tend to be looking
for those opportunities to sort of
simplify and modularize and componentize
the applications so i think that's one
aspect of it is sort of the code
management and how how a code base
evolves that's one that's really
important and maybe we'll talk more
about it later but bringing in some of
these other tools like testing like
package management those sorts of things
as it gets more and more complex we have
ways to really lock in the behavior of
different pieces of this and version the
behavior of pieces of infrastructure
yeah now it's infrastructure as compiled
packages that you deliver which we will
definitely get more into as we go but
speaking of that sort of thing if i'm
doing infrastructure as code and say i'm
in you know an environment like in java
i'm using maybe i'm using maven and net
i'm using nougat i'm in typescript i'm
using npm whatever it might be if my
typically using just what a vendor that
i've chosen has given me or am i also
leveraging other existing
packages out there to help sort of add
to what i can do with iac
yeah i think that's one of the really
exciting things i think you know the
sort of answer is both but i think it's
also something that i think is shifting
more and more now with these iac tools
you have access to the raw building
blocks that the cloud providers provide
right so sort of everything available in
aws everything available in azure
everything available cloudflare you kind
of have the raw api that the cloud
providers you know so you can do
everything but those tend to be
low-level building blocks right and for
a lot of folks going and figuring out
again from first principles how do i
connect you know all these different
pieces i need together there's a lot of
people reinventing the wheel on how to
build a best practices vpc and natw
right
and so then there are sort of libraries
that can be built on top of that
which are that best practices vpc hey i
don't need to go and put together those
15 building blocks myself every time i
can just go and use this higher level
building block that has built into it
with some coarse grain parameterization
here's a way to sort of get the most
common patterns for how to configure a
best practices vpc as documented by aws
and now i can you know for most purposes
for the common 90 case i can just use
that and write a few lines of code and i
get all the infrastructure i need and so
those kind of libraries whether it's
libraries that you know you build as an
end user or is it for your organization
to capture your best practices or
whether it's part of something that's
available in the open source or from a
vendor as part of a higher level library
they create i think that's a place where
we're seeing more and more of that
reusable infrastructure libraries being
built out now i'd say it's still
relatively early for that but i think
there's going to be
a lot of progress that just as the
complexity folks are trying to manage
keeps to go up keeps going up we're
going to see that continue to be an area
where that ecosystem grows and something
we're doing a lot of work to try and
kind of build out that ecosystem around
kind of the palumi model but it's
something that you know we're also
plugging into all the other existing
ecosystems whether it's right helm
charts or cloud formation templates or
arm templates or other things where
there might be ecosystems of reusable
components of infrastructure that could
go some really interesting stuff and
we'll talk future more at the end but
i've got a bunch of synapses firing
right now thinking about well i want a
template that's going to let me run my
system with these components you know
what happens if i run it on you know
postgres with sqs what happens if i run
it over here with you know and
azure service bus or whatever just like
i don't know
run both what do they cost how do they
benchmark how do they this and it seems
like that's the sort of thing
we might even be moving more into as we
can automate these things and define
them in more consistent templatized
kinds of ways which could be really
really interesting you kind of took it
even one step further which i think is a
few interesting ways that i think are
really interesting
you know they're sort of building
reusable libraries that just take a
single pattern on a single cloud
provider and give it a name but there's
a lot of patterns that can make sense
across multiple cloud providers right
some of the basic run run a postgres
database and a linux vm hey we can run
that on any cloud so maybe we can build
that you know component as an interface
that i can sort of develop to
and now i can instantiate that on any
cloud provider right because the the
differences between the cloud providers
while there might be some performance
differences and those kind of things
just like i can run java or net on a
variety of different platforms i can in
theory run my cloud application on a
variety of different platforms and so
that kind of that abstraction capability
also starts to get into kind of how can
we think about multi-cloud and that sort
of thing
visit lenovo.com se radio and see why
lenode has been voted the top
infrastructure as a service provider by
both g2 and trust radius from their
award-winning support offered 24 7 365
to every level of user to ease of use
and setup it's clear why developers have
been trusting lenode for projects both
big and small since 2003. lenode offers
the industry's best price to performance
value for all compute instances
including shared dedicated high memory
gpus and their upcoming bare metal
release lenod makes cloud computing
simple affordable and accessible
allowing you to focus on your customers
not your infrastructure want to learn
more about infrastructure as code and
terraform visit lenode.com that's
l-i-n-o-d-e
s-e-radio and download their e-book
understanding terraform and other
resources for free today
so i've adopted ise we've got a
repository we've got our definitions in
there we're starting to get this thing
going and now i need to actually apply
these definitions
so talk a little bit about that aspect
of iac you know imagine maybe at first
there's some manual aspects to it maybe
you then can begin to automate some of
these things try to move towards full
automation and in that context too
i'm very curious to know about the fact
that engineers don't ask how can we make
this thing work engineers ask what's
going to break what's going to go wrong
so when we're talking about applying
these things things like monitoring
fault tolerance recovery are going to be
really important as well so give us kind
of a flavor of i want to adopt this i'm
starting to learn it but now i need to
actually do this stuff out in the wild
and how am i going to do that
effectively a few different layers on
this and i think a lot of what i'll talk
about is sort of true for most
infrastructure code tools so the last
step maybe is something that we're doing
some interesting work on with pollution
i think but the first step is really
i've written some new desired statement
i want to i want to deploy that i want
to say hey i want to make that desired
state be my real state that i've gotten
cloud provider and i'm going to do that
you know using a cli command for example
i'm going to run you know aws cloud
formation you know deploy what have you
and i'm just going to say whatever code
i've got i want to make that the truth
right so that kind of cli based workflow
is really the starting point that most
folks use for getting started with
infrastructure's code is that i'm going
to use a cli to to deploy that
infrastructure and i'm going to sort of
interactively
understand what the state of that
deployment is i'm going to see sort of
the status of what's deploying i'm going
to if something goes wrong to your point
i'm going to
understand that sort of synchronously
during the deployment because i'm
watching that cli output and i'm going
to go and take some corrective action
based on what that error message is or
whatever i'm going to fix up my desired
state if it was actually a an invalid
desired state and so that's why it
failed i'm going to fix it up and then
rerun that deployment and move to that
new fixed up state what have you and so
i think that's where a lot of folks
start that's where ise traditionally has
kind of been focused that's a good
starting point what teams working in you
know production environments want though
is they don't want to rely on some
operator sitting at their machine
running commands that are modifying the
cloud right uh they want to move that
into cross-shared processes that are
typically a sort of continuous delivery
process or something like that
where
changes to
infrastructure are pushed through kind
of a delivery pipeline like they're
driven by a git process where you're
going to push that code into a
particular branch and uh there's going
to be pr and the pr is going to show a
preview of what changes might get made
to the cloud provider and someone's
going to review that and say yes i
accept and this is okay to deploy and
now when we deploy that we're going to
sort of see that process through a
continuous delivery pipeline and so
that's one of the great things we can
take all of that those same tools that
we used on our desktop we can move those
into a ci cd kind of environment and
take advantage of all that sort of
continuous delivery infrastructure that
we've got but use it not just for
application delivery but for delivery of
changes to our infrastructure itself so
that's where we see you know most
serious iec users today are kind of
doing that they're putting their isc
tools into continuous delivery the last
step is one that we've been working on
at preliminary something that we call
automation api and this is a thing that
we actually saw was a lot of the teams
we're working with who really are
sort of software teams trying to manage
cloud infrastructure they were looking
to go beyond just ci cd and kind of
build their own custom software
solutions that managed the delivery of
infrastructure changes so where they
could really deeply customize
what steps happened in between different
parts of the cloud infrastructure
changes they could author that as
software they could version our software
and so automation api was sort of a way
to embed the deployment of cloud
infrastructure into
your own software solutions that could
be hey i'm building my own sort of
self-service provisioning portal where
users can come up and say i want an
instance of this thing and so that's
going to go and kick off a deployment of
that thing or i want to change this
configuration setting or whatever they
can build up that application as a piece
of software and it's going to drive a
whole bunch of infrastructure delivery
processes on the banking i see that
being kind of a next wave of like how we
drive infrastructure delivery is going
to be these sort of custom software
solutions that folks build that aren't
just a citd workflow but are even more
to the metal automated solutions and
we're seeing you know we've seen a ton
of folks doing really interesting things
with that automation api and i think
that's something we're going to see in a
lot of other places we also see variants
of that in the kubernetes space which is
the operator models and that sort of
thing where folks find really
interesting extensibility models into
into kubernetes that are kind of based
around some of the same ideas of
software-driven automation of
infrastructure changes and so that's a
trend that sort of more nascent but is
is going to be really interesting over
the next few years
and really that triggers for me even a
bigger concept of maybe listeners are
familiar with some of the workflow
engines that are out there like i know
netflix has conductor there's apache
airflow and speaking of monitoring fault
tolerance recovery these kinds of things
and this is the first time i've thought
of those tools in this kind of a context
because typically i'm thinking of those
in terms of a workflow for a business
process for a customer that we're trying
to build software for but it seems like
you could take that automation api as
you're describing it maybe it already
does some of these things or maybe it
needs that bigger kind of workflow
engine but now that ability to say yes i
have my desired state but steps could
happen they go wrong i need to retry or
need to whatever it might be and how do
you see that stuff kind of playing out
as well and taking this kind of
even workflow automation for these sorts
of things there's both those sort of
more generic workflow solutions the kind
of things you mentioned as you say are
mostly about kind of business processes
that sort of thing i'd say there's a set
of these that are kind of being
developed over the last couple of years
in the market that are more focused on
devops kind of scenarios things like
puppets relay things like chemical
filaments there's doing some interesting
stuff there there's a set of
technologies i've seen kind of being
developed that do try to apply some of
the same ideas but into
into some of the specific nuances of
kind of the devops workflows and
automating those things and a lot of the
times things like infrastructure's code
deployments are steps in those workflows
but to your point there's a more complex
workflow that needs to be managed on top
of that and supporting those kind of
tools is one of the scenarios for things
like automation api but i think those
take that another step further where
they build sort of declarative processes
on top of how we manage that you know
i'm not sure exactly where that class of
things will go i think that's also
reasonably early but i do think
capturing as many of these processes in
software of some kind is something
that's just a trend that you know is
always going to be there right if we can
capture workflow processes and
repeatable
software-based solutions that's going to
help us to scale those processes for
sure and that's something that's true
across every industry
some things it depends on the nature of
your business in each of your use case
some things are always going to be
easier and something's always going to
be harder depending on what you're doing
and one of the difficulties i think as
we start moving more into some of the
depth i think of testing and things of
this nature with iac what's really nice
to be able to do is to basically stand
up a
near production environment with and
i'll call it production quality data you
might have to sanitize pii or personally
identify information these kinds of
things but also that's tricky if you're
uber you don't get to do that because
you have way too much data to do that
but can i see help if maybe i'm not uber
and most of our listeners aren't with
that kind of thing where i can actually
say i want to hit a full production
environment with production quality data
and when i confirm it
flip that over and kind of a blue green
deployment sort of an approach
yeah i think there's a whole bunch of
sort of different patterns there that
are interesting but i do think that that
sort of iac solutions generally can be a
big part of it i think one of the first
things along that path is just hey the
ability to even create another copy of
my environments right i mean if i've
written down the description of what my
infrastructure is
i at least have some hope that i can you
know recreate it right whether that's
just to create a one-off staging
environment that i can use or whether
that's to every developer can stand up
their own version of the environment or
you know some of the things that you
know we do this internally for some of
our stuff but we've seen a lot of our
customers do interesting things around
us where
every pr that they open is going to
stand up a whole new copy of the
infrastructure and that copy is going to
go away when the pr is closed right but
that you know that could be either the
whole infrastructure it could be a
subset infrastructure but they use
infrastructure's code as a way to
describe what is that thing i'm going to
stand up a copy of
on every one of these instantiations and
what i'm going to parameterize that via
some settings that maybe the user can
control but at least i have that
repeatable process where i can go and
stand this up and tear it down as soon
as you have that ability to stand up
your infrastructure again that opens up
so many interesting possibilities it
does it opens up staging environments
opens up per developer environments it
opens up these sort of review apps kind
of style pr things it opens up testing
abilities now my tests can stand up an
environment run a bunch of tests against
it and tear it down instead of having to
test against against a production
environment but i think to your point
it's not just the infrastructure there
right it's so how do i get the data
seeded into that thing how do i get you
know there's a few other things i might
need to do to sort of get that
environment to really
represent something production-like
enough so that i can sort of validate
what i need to validate right and i
think that's where one of the
interesting things with some of the more
modern infrastructures code tools is
they really give a lot of flexibility
for how you intertwine kind of
management of infrastructure with taking
specific actions and so if you need to
run database migrations or do seeding of
your database you need to sort of
intertwine some actions into that
deployment there's a lot of tools to
sort of reach out of the kind of pure
desired state model and into hey i'm
going to write some custom code here
that goes and
runs a command against you know i just
stood up my sql instance
in the cloud and now i'm going to run
some commands to sort imperatively put
some data into that thing to seed it or
to pull that data over from some other
environment where i already did that
data cleaning whatever so i think like a
lot of these ic tools you know even
though their primary focus is around
managing cloud infrastructure there's a
lot of ways to go and break out of that
and sort of run some custom logic that
can help you to define the pieces of
your environment that aren't just
managed by cloud apis
now let's say i create a desired state
definition
and
let's say i have two environments
running and they're actually different
for whatever reason set aside the
arbitrary nature of my setup here but
i'm curious when i've defined this is a
tool like palumi or terraform is it
creating a diff of my desired state
versus actual state or do i have to
actually make sure that whatever desired
state i'm defining is already pegged to
a particular
sort of like database migrations i can
define a new database and then the
migrations are going to be specific to
the state of the actual database
but it's nice if i can just declare the
state i want and say well database a is
a little different than database b but
the tool just figures out the right
migrations for both how do the tools
kind of help with that sort of thing the
iec tools
yeah in general you know a lot of these
tools have the ability to that they do
keep track of what state the environment
is in just because it's typically
expensive to try and recover all of that
state from the cloud providers they
manage their their own view and so then
they can compute hey this is the delta i
need to apply right they typically have
options for refreshing that data pulling
that data out of the cloud provider and
understanding what that drift is between
what's the desired state that i
understood the world to be in based on
the last time i did deployment and
what's what's the actual state of the
world and so we can then go see that
diff see what has changed and then
decide whether we want to
kind of drive that back into the desired
state that i'm managing or else i can
make changes to my desired safe to say
no that was an intentional change my
desired state is just wrong maybe i
somebody went in and said i want four
instances instead of two and i haven't
yet changed my desired state i don't
want to undo that i want to actually
just represent that back in my state so
so they can go make that change now when
they do that refresh it won't say
there's a diff and and everything will
be okay so there is that process of sort
of reconciling those two things
understanding when drift has happened
and then sort of taking action to
correct that either in the real estate
or in the desired state well i think
that's a good segue to talk some about
security in the infrastructure's code
world you know in an ideal world nobody
can touch your database your migrations
are pristine and they're always working
against the state you expect in the real
world somebody can get an essay password
and bypass all that somebody can go to
your aws portal and spin up a new
instance of something or or mess with
things
there's a couple aspects to security
here as well i mean i guess one of them
is security around who can create the
definitions but i think that's pretty
straightforward standard software
engineering practices but i think more
interesting is how do you check the
security of the infrastructure that
you're wanting to stand up that's one
and then also dealing with compliance
who can deploy what infrastructure you
know somebody says i want a kate's
cluster that's the biggest case cluster
that's ever been built and it's going to
cost a million dollars an hour okay we
got to deal with that too so
security kind of like how am i deploying
secure cloud systems and how can iec
help with that and then also security
around you can't do that
yeah i mean so obviously obviously an
interesting balance on a bunch of
directions because you know security
piece is really important but then
there's also that everyone wants to
provide the sort of developer velocity
and how do we empower folks to have as
much capability as they should have
without having any of the capability
they shouldn't have so uh and that's a
tight balance because sometimes those
are really conflicting it's like
parenting give your kids all the freedom
they can handle and no
more yeah
it's exactly sort of the same content
i'd say a couple of things you know one
that i think is a starting point for me
for this is just the the cloud providers
have just an amazing set of capabilities
built in around security and managing
security that's really the starting
point is understanding taking advantage
of all the primitives that are available
at various different levels to manage
security whether it's at the im level
whether it's at the sort of network
protection level whether it's the
account level there's a whole bunch of
layers of sort of you can apply
different security practices that are
typically built into these cloud apis at
a pretty deep level and they have
incredible building blocks to work from
there
so the first answer is sort of the
infrastructure's code just lets you use
all those building blocks right and so a
lot of what you're doing when you're
kind of managing security practices by
infrastructure's code aren't necessarily
specific to the infrastructure code tool
they're just about
you know taking advantage of all those
primitives and taking advantage of all
those building blocks you can use to
bake those security practices into
the infrastructure patterns you're using
now i think as part of that that tends
to be well we talked earlier about
creating best practices
reusable components well of course those
best practices reusable components have
security best practices in them as well
right so i can capture those best
practices once i can then have everyone
in my organization use the same thing if
i if i realize that there's some
hardening i want to do around that
component i can do it in one place and
everyone else benefits from it the same
sort of things that help with sort of
application security right where i can
actually rely on the building block and
building on top of is secure by design
and so now i get all these benefits from
it that's really the core thing there
are some things that the
infrastructure's code layer that i think
are really interesting around security
and there's sort of two pieces that i
think of one is you kind of talked about
the automation piece and moving from
here developers on their machine just
going and running some command and the
environment you've got is that the
developer just is copy pasting some
production credentials onto the machine
and they're running a command
eventually you're going to run into some
problems right and the security of your
deployment is going to have some issues
and so
folks typically are doing that where
they're they're creating continuous
delivery pipelines or something like
that where there's privileged agents
capable of doing deployments into the
production environment but there are a
whole bunch of checks in place whether
it's manual gating approvals or
code reviews or what have you that are
going to make sure that only things
which are kind of approved have been
validated have been run a preview that
we know what kind of changes this is
going to make and so the review has
gotten a chance to see that ahead of
time but there's a bunch of process and
sort of validation in the same way that
hey if i'm building a mobile app and i
want to deploy that out to the world i'm
going to put a whole bunch of gates in
place to make sure that only a build
that actually works and that has been
validated and it doesn't have some
trojan horse built into it i'm going to
put all these checks inside to make sure
that that's a good thing
the same thing we can do kind of in our
in our continuous delivery and
infrastructure's code really works very
well inside those environments to help
me understand those previews help me
understand what changes
and then i did say the last piece is
policy and that's something that a lot
of the infrastructure code tools offer
we offered for palomi kind of have a way
of describing
associated with infrastructure so things
that have to be true about my
infrastructure for it to deploy
correctly
and so i can have my compliance team or
my security team build out a set of
policies that are going to apply to any
infrastructure i deploy or maybe any
infrastructure that's going to deploy
into my production environment and say
hey like you cannot open up a
new public ip address in this vpc or
something like that without getting an
approval for that or you cannot make a
s3 bucket public or that sort of thing
and so we can put this policy in place
and now these tools will
enforce that policy on any deployments
that happen using environment with
pulley for example we can actually use
software to describe our policy as well
right so we can build reusable policy
abstractions we can build arbitrarily
sort of rich ways of doing it maybe for
cost for example i can go pull down the
aws price sheet i can go compute the
cost of everything and i can say hey
your cost increased by you know when i
tried to deploy this giant kubernetes
cluster your cost increased by a million
dollars an hour so you probably don't
want to deploy this right put a big red
mark in my deployment that's going
through that continuous delivery
pipeline and just warn that reviewer
that hey you probably shouldn't accept
this because it's going to increase your
costs and then calculating that before
you ran it is it right which i think
it's kind of exactly what you can do
right yeah yeah
you can see that during that preview the
reviewer before they merge that into
production can see that and they can say
no we have to make this change before we
go and deploy that so those are the
sorts of things i think you can do and
there's like there's a ton more richness
that can be built with the kind of
modern compliance policy tools that are
available now absolutely and speaking of
that maybe a bit of a side note but are
vendors like palumi or others are they
sort of reinventing policy or is there
potential for adoption of you know you
mentioned cloud native before and of
course there's the cncf cloud native
computing foundation which leads me to
think of something called open policy
agent
so is there an ability to use existing
tools in the ecosystem to apply policies
within an iac context yeah so i think
there's a whole bunch of different
answers for different data i know we
don't want to go too deep into that it's
a little orthogonal but i thought it was
at least interesting in the subject of
compliance to talk about a little bit
policy agent obviously has been growing
really fast over the last couple of
years here and you know especially in
kind of a kubernetes space but really
expanding to a lot of other spaces as
well with our preliminary policy
solution we let you write those policies
in you know in the existing languages
that we have like typescript and python
and things but we also let you write it
in open policy agent which sort of its
own has its own language yeah regular
which i can link to in the show notes
exactly yep so it lets you kind of write
rego-based rules and then use open
policy agent as the execution engine for
those rules but
instead of enforcing that policy against
the kubernetes manifest you can force
that against the plume deployment i
think there's a lot of interesting stuff
going on in this space and i think all
the vendors but certainly palumi really
trying to integrate into and let folks
bring
places where places where there is a lot
of innovation happening let's bring that
in and let folks use that with our
infrastructure's code tools but the core
thing is we want to make it so that you
can plug that policy solution into
the paloomy execution of your of your
cloud infrastructure deployments whether
that's using you know typescript to
python or using rego i actually think
that's a great story because options is
a good thing to have people need options
like you know we mentioned before that
using the gui to stand up cloud
infrastructure it's not right wrong good
bad it's different and there's a context
for it it becomes bad when the
complexity becomes unmaintainable or
it's too easy to break it and that's
when it's time so in a similar fashion i
think it's great that there's options
here you can use the language you're
familiar with
but you might have and i think this is
coming we're going to have more and more
people who are super familiar with opa
and rego and that's going to become a
possibly a specialization all of its own
and to be able to leverage that asset
that resource that knowledge and plug
that into this whole iac pipeline i
think has a lot of promise so that's
really cool to hear that that's an
option even already yeah it's an option
now but i think it's something that's
going to be i agree with you i think
it's going to be an even bigger thing as
we move forward and as the
specialization does grow even even
larger around not authoring the
infrastructure but offering the policy
around the infrastructure because
there's a ton of richness
as well so now from that kind of big
scale discussion right how do i manage
all this infrastructure and all the
policies and compliance and the costs
and everything now let's bring it down
to i'm a developer and i'm doing iac and
i want to be able to test and for me and
i know for a lot of our listeners as
well it's important to try it as much as
you can to be able to run things locally
you know when the wi-fi dies if i can't
get to my cloud provider and i can't
develop that is a bad situation to be in
so from the spectrum of fully isolated
testing in my own environment using iac
to maybe some integration testing with
cloud resources because i want to check
how things are going to work with near
production type provisioned resources
tell us a little bit about the testing
landscape with iac kind of along that
spectrum when you're doing application
development
you largely want that to be as isolated
as it can be from from any of its
dependencies in the sense right and so
you want to be able to run that
application locally you want to be able
to sort of do that inner loop of
development on that iterate really
quickly inside the application code base
for that piece you want to have the
local database that you can use instead
of having to go out to the cloud
whatever it is you do for your
application development iec typically
doesn't have as much of a role there
because obviously you're trying to keep
everything locally where testing really
starts to impact iec is in a few
different places so one is once you do
have infras cloud infrastructure that
you're managing as part of your your
solution well a
you want to make sure that
infrastructure does what it says it does
right so you want to be able to validate
things
the value of the things are true about
that infrastructure and so i think of
that as sort of unit testing your
infrastructure where you write hey
you've got your infrastructure
description over here but now i'm going
to write some things i believe need to
be true about the results of that
infrastructure so especially as i build
more and more complex components that
describe infrastructure i want to say
well if i'm building this best practices
vpc component and i say i want three
subnets well let's let me make sure that
there really were three subnets created
let me really make sure that they have
non-overlapping cider ranges right i
think i'm in my desired state but am i
really
yeah but a lot of this is things that i
can just say i don't even have to deploy
my infrastructure i can just validate
that my desired state program
describes something that has this to be
true and so so i think a unit testing
piece is just me writing down all the
sort of contracts of what things need to
be true and just validating that that
can be very fast it can be validated as
just as part of unit testing
infrastructure without having to deploy
it i think then sort of validating
things are true when i deploy that's
where actually a lot of the policy tools
we just talked about can come in because
they can validate things as i'm
deploying infrastructure or even when
i'm previewing the planning
infrastructure i can say well i need to
validate that this is true and i want to
fail immediately if something is not
true because that indicates i'm outside
of the sort of state i want it to be in
and i want to go and take some
remediation action so i think policy
tools can sort of be part of a testing
solution at that layer as well
and then the last which i sort of think
of is the most interesting
is sort of the integration testing
and that's where kind of being able to
stand up environments or subsets of
environments from scratch is really
interesting where to test some
components if i can go and just create a
production-like environment then run all
of my application level tests against
that but where the environment is real
right i'm actually using real cloud
infrastructure i'm using the real
network topology i'm going to run it i'm
using the real you know a database that
is configured exactly the same as my
production database just maybe with
different data inside it
that can give me a whole bunch of
confidence that not just my application
is correct but the infrastructure that
i'm wanting to run my application in and
especially as increasingly we're having
to change both our application code and
our infrastructure kind of in lockstep
we're making changes to we've got a
serverless application everywhere
changing
we're adding in some new data service
that's going to trigger a serverless
function and so the code i need to write
and the data servers that i'm connecting
to are kind of being co-developed and so
now i really want to when i want to test
that i really want to be able to stand
up a copy of that environment validate
that not just the code does what it says
it does but that it does what it
needs to do relative to the data source
is going to trigger it
and so
yes that is something that i can't just
validate entirely on my machine
but it's something that's essential to
my application and so i need to test it
and if i can make it so that that whole
environment is something i can stand up
really quickly
run my test against and tear down
now that opens up so many possibilities
for me creating you know much more
confidence now when i open up that pr
i can run this battery of tests to
validate that the application and the
infrastructure work correctly together i
can get that green check mark and now i
feel confident that when i merge into
production it's going to work correctly
that category of testing is really where
infrastructure's code
tends to unlock
really fundamentally new things that
give me significantly more confidence in
my deployments and then what about
auditing the production environments and
that's another way to test is you know
let's say i've configured you know my
kubernetes cluster to you know have a
minimum number of nodes with these pods
and then a maximum number you know so i
don't like blow the budget or whatever
these things might be our iec tool is
able to kind of help me with that
auditing and monitoring piece as well of
production assets yes i think one piece
is by kind of some of the drift
detection i talked about earlier where
we kind of go and understand pull that
state back in and understand whether
it's changed from the desired state and
then combining that with the policy
solutions gives us the ability to
enforce policy against
the real state but if you want that more
live typically the cloud providers
themselves have kind of policy solutions
that live inside the infrastructure and
it can be even tighter to that like aws
config or something like that but the
place where desired state infrastructure
is code
can come in really helpful there is i
think what a lot of folks do is they do
interesting things where they build
custom solutions for kind of testing and
production where they're whether it's
chaos engineering and really advanced
kind of things like that or it's just
simple things where hey i'm going to run
a workload against you know i'm just
going to be constantly running a
background canary workload against my
application so that i just have some
constant load and i'm able to see how
that's behaving and things like that
they're not you know they're custom
solutions they're things i'm going to
build they're just kind of another piece
of structure but they tend to be just
more iac right they tend to be here's
three more pieces i'm going to deploy
into production as part of my
environment and if i do that with iac
well hey i can actually get all of that
even when i'm standing up this staging
environment right so now my staging
environment can have that canary job
running inside as well because i've
described that in a in a repeatable way
and so we find that often these ise
tools unlock the ability to sort of
build a lot more of those kind of
solutions into the applications the
application kind of knows how to have
its own
sort of test and production
infrastructure embedded into it as part
of how i deploy that and i can get that
in all my different environments plummy
terraform the other ones that are sort
of in this third wave you described
earlier how are these actually executing
is there a runtime that's running
somewhere in my cloud environment or am
i running something in a
ci cd you know container speak a little
bit because i think that kind of helps
answer some of these questions too about
things like audit and things like that
you know you mentioned canary thing but
you're building that yourself so how
does it kind of work in that standpoint
from a runtime standpoint an actual when
you execute these things yes i think a
lot of that comes back into some of
these questions about well what is it a
manual deployment or is it a ci cd
deployment automated deployment and
really the end of the day these iec
tools tend to be some piece of software
somewhere that's that's running that is
gonna you know when you ask it to change
to a new desired state it's gonna move
you to that new desired state that could
be a cli tool it could be a cli embedded
in the cicd workflow where when i keep
that workflow it pulls out the
latest git commit and it pushes me to
that state or it could be some other
more advanced workflow like we were
talking about with some of these
workflow engines that might be built on
top of that so really you can embed
these things into a lot of different
environments whether as just tools or
software packages or services iec itself
i think isn't prescriptive around that i
think it kind of depends on how what
shortfalls you build that into but yeah
i think in general we see folks moving
towards those more automated solutions
for sure but they tend to be running
from outside of the cloud environment in
a sense right they tend to be modifying
the cloud environment they're sort of
part of the control plane effectively
the customer is using to manage their
cloud cloud environment the sort of data
plane of that deployment is what lives
inside the cloud and that is going to be
all the various pieces and that's sort
of where i make that distinction that
there's a lot of interesting things you
might want to build to put in that data
plane right you might want to build this
canary deployment into your actual cloud
deployment you might want to build use
some of the edible services for security
and compliance that sort of thing so i
think you kind of have those options to
use iac to describe that but also the
options to during that deployment
process with your iec tool in force
policy and those sorts of things well
this has been a fascinating exploration
i think of iac and
i want to wrap up by asking you a more
future looking question related somewhat
to iac but also more broadly how do you
think cloud tools are going to shape the
future in a what we hope will soon be a
post covet 19 world the economy is
changing the world is changing so how
are cloud tools and and maybe iec
specifically what do you envision them
doing over the next you know five to ten
years yeah obviously you know the last
year year and a half or so have been
absolutely abnormal in a lot of ways but
one of the things that you know you've
seen as a consequence of everything
that's been happening has just been kind
of every organization realizing
how important software is how important
the cloud is to their business and how
much leverage that they can get for
continuing to have impact with their
business via software and via the cloud
and so i think the first part of the
answer to this is i think cloud is going
to continue to be a
even more significant factor in how
organizations are investing and building
for their future
everyone who didn't already believe that
has been taught
taught a lot of new lessons about how
important that is but even the people
who really did believe it are just
realizing the scale at which they can
get value out of out of the cloud
absolutely that can drive their business
so i think that's the backdrop for it
and then i think these tools have been
maybe a little bit of a broken record on
this but i think one of the things that
you know i just see over and over again
is that as you want to take advantage of
the cloud you want to take advantage of
building blocks that really are
incredibly valuable
getting all that value out is going to
require building more and more complex
solutions on top of that that's a good
thing because those complex solutions
the more complex that means the more
value you're getting but now all these
tools have to come and take up the
burden of how do we manage that
complexity how do we build software
engineering teams that know how to
manage very large amounts of complexity
in the cloud for companies that are
really going to lead their industries in
how they take advantage of the cloud
they're going to be bringing in these
engineers who are able to
manage the cloud at scale and build at
scale solutions on top of the cloud and
i think that's where cloud development
tools generally and in ise specifically
are going to play important roles in
helping those teams to continue to build
amazing things to take advantage of
everything in the cloud
this episode of se radio is exclusively
sponsored by lenode the node makes cloud
computing simple affordable and
accessible whether you're working on a
personal project or looking for someone
to manage your company's infrastructure
lenode has the pricing support security
and scale you need with lenod you get
consistent and predictable pricing
across 11 global markets 24x7 by 365
human support rich documentation and
policies and controls to strengthen your
overall security posture allowing you to
grow at your own pace
users consistently rank lenode as one of
the leading public cloud providers on
both g2 and trust radius want to learn
more about infrastructure as code and
terraform visit lenode.com that's
l-i-n-o-d-e
s e radio and download their ebook
understanding terraform and other
resources for free today
well luke if people want to find out
more about what you're up to where would
you send them yeah twitter at lucon
github
github.com look open feel free to drop
me a note in either of those places and
of course everything we're doing at
palumi great so all the familiar places
all right well thank you so much for
joining me today on software engineering
radio hikers great to be here this is
jeff doolittle thanks for
listening thanks for listening to sc
radio an educational program brought to
you by ieee software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se
radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening